Anthropology Division Archives
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
Anthropology Division Archives
1902-2014
ANTAR.000009
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
50
approximately; plus 8 file cabinets and 1 map case
The miscellaneous archives of the Division of Anthropology.
Div. of Anthropology, Yale Peabody Museum
Biographical Sketch
The establishment of the Division of Anthropology at the Yale Peabody Museum in 1902 by George Grant MacCurdy brought together the Museum's archaeological, ethnological and physical anthropology collections under a single authority. Since then, through the University's scientific expeditions and donations from Yale alumni and friends, the holdings of the Division have grown to over 280,000 catalogued lots.
While Othniel Charles Marsh is best known for his paleontological research, during his association with the Museum significant anthropological collections were also acquired, many through the Yale Scientific Expeditions, or through the efforts of individuals.
The Anthropology Division collections include both Connecticut and Old World artifacts acquired by MacCurdy, as well as a large collection of pottery from Panama that he published in 1911. Some of MacCurdy's most interesting collections are those from the American School for Prehistoric Research's summer field programs in Europe in the 1920s and 1930s.
Although not an anthropologist by training, nor formally affiliated with the Peabody, Hiram Bingham's rediscovery of Peru's Machu Picchu brought archaeological material from the site, along with associated documents and photographs, to the Division.
Cornelius Osgood was Curator of Anthropology from 1934 to 1973 and brought significant collections to the Museum from his research expeditions to the Arctic, China and Korea. Osgood may be best known for his research among the Athapaskan-speaking people of interior Alaska, much of it published through the Yale University Publications in Anthropology series. He was also active in Connecticut archaeology.
Froelich Rainey was an assistant curator of anthropology from 1935 to 1937 and contributed to the Caribbean and Connecticut archaeological collections. Wendell Bennett was a research associate in anthropology from 1945 to 1953. Bennett's major contribution to the anthropology collections were in South American archaeology, particularly the Huari material from Peru and other collections from Columbia and Ecuador that are curated by the Museum.
(Benjamin) Irving Rouse's research has given the Peabody one of the world's largest collections of systematically excavated archaeological material from the Caribbean, comprising 52 percent of the Division's catalog records and hundreds of thousands of individual objects. (For more on Ben Rouse, see "Passing of a Pioneer Researcher in Caribbean Archaeology," by Dr. Basil Reid, March 12, 2006, in UWIToday, a monthly magazine produced by the Office of the Campus Principal of the University of the West Indies, St. Augustine.)
Description of the Material
The archives of the Division of Anthropolgy include paintings, photographs, maps, lantern slides and 35mm slides.
Correspondence; Ledgers; Maps; Photographs; Yale University
- Paintings, Prints, Photographs, Series I
  - African Culture., 026268
  - Asian Culture., 028199
  - Caribbean Culture., 028200
  - European Culture., 028201
  - Latin American: Central America Culture., 028202
  - Latin American: Central Andes: Inca Culture., 028203
  - Latin American: MesoAmerica Culture., 028204
  - Latin American: South America Culture., 028205
  - Miscellaneous., 028218
  - North American Culture., 028214
  - North American: California Culture., 028206
  - North American: Eastern Woodland Culture., 028207
  - North American: Eskimo Culture., 028209
  - North American: Great Basin Culture., 028208
  - North American: North Pacific Coast Culture., 028210
  - North American: Plains Culture., 028211
  - North American: Southeast Culture., 028212
  - North American: Southwest Culture., 028213
  - Object Photographs, Negatives and Color Transparencies. Box 1 of 6. 298 photographs, negatives and color transparencies of objects in the Peabody's Antropology collection. The contents of this box have not been scanned or catalogued and are for objects with catalogue numbers in the range ANT.000001 to ANT.009999. Photographs, negatives and transparencies are approximately 4x5 inches in size or smaller. Box contents are from Peabody's photography (PF) files and some new media., 042016
  - Object Photographs, Negatives and Color Transparencies. Box 2 of 6. 268 photographs, negatives and color transparencies of objects in the Peabody's Antropology collection. The contents of this box have not been scanned or catalogued and are for objects with catalogue numbers in the range ANT.010000 to ANT.050500. Photographs, negatives and transparencies are approximately 4x5 inches in size or smaller. Box contents are from Peabody's photography (PF) files and some new media., 042017
  - Object Photographs, Negatives and Color Transparencies. Box 3 of 6. 254 photographs, negatives and color transparencies of objects in the Peabody's Antropology collection. The contents of this box have not been scanned or catalogued and are for objects with catalogue numbers in the range ANT.050501 to ANT.209500. Photographs, negatives and transparencies are approximately 4x5 inches in size or smaller. Box contents are from Peabody's photography (PF) files and some new media., 042018
  - Object Photographs, Negatives and Color Transparencies. Box 4 of 6. 218 photographs, negatives and color transparencies of objects in the Peabody's Antropology collection. The contents of this box have not been scanned or catalogued and are for objects with catalogue numbers in the range ANT.209501 to ANT.236748. Photographs, negatives and transparencies are approximately 4x5 inches in size or smaller. Box contents are from Peabody's photography (PF) files and some new media., 042019
  - Object Photographs, Negatives and Color Transparencies. Box 5 of 6. 254 photographs, negatives and color transparencies of objects in the Peabody's Antropology collection. The contents of this box have not been scanned or catalogued and are for objects with catalogue numbers in the range ANT.236749 to ANT.257100. Photographs, negatives and transparencies are approximately 4x5 inches in size or smaller. Box contents are from Peabody's photography (PF) files and some new media., 042020
  - Object Photographs, Negatives and Color Transparencies. Box 6 of 6. 246 photographs, negatives and color transparencies of objects in the Peabody's Antropology collection. The contents of this box have not been scanned or catalogued. 245 are for objects with catalogue numbers in the range ANT.257101 to ANT.257194. One negative corresponds to ANTPA.004339/004452. Photographs, negatives and transparencies are approximately 4x5 inches in size or smaller. Box contents are from Peabody's photography (PF) files and some new media., 042021
  - Oceanian Culture., 028217
  - Oceanian: Australia Culture., 028215
  - Oceanian: Polynesia Culture., 028216
- Maps, 1902-Present; Series II
  - Africa., 024999
  - Asia., 025000
  - Caribbean., 025909
  - Europe., 025001
  - Latin America: Central America., 024997
  - Latin America: Miscellaneous., 025003
  - Latin America: South America., 024998
  - Miscellaneous., 025910
  - North America: Arctic., 024989
  - North America: California., 024990
  - North America: Eastern Woodland., 024991
  - North America: Great Basin., 024992
  - North America: Miscellaneous., 024996
  - North America: Plains., 024993
  - North America: Southeast., 024994
  - North America: Southwest., 024995
  - Oceania., 025002
- Lantern Slides, Series III
  - African Culture., 001047
  - Asian Culture., 001049
  - Caribbean Culture., 001050
  - European Culture., 001048
  - Latin American Culture., 001045
  - Miscellaneous., 002313
  - North American Culture., 000790
  - Oceanian Culture., 001051
  - South American Culture., 001046
- Small Slides, Series IV
  - African Culture., 002414
  - Asian Culture., 002416
  - Caribbean Culture., 002417
  - European Culture., 002415
  - Latin American Culture., 002413
  - Miscellaneous., 002419
  - North American Culture., 002412
  - Oceanian Culture., 002418
  - Asian Culture: Korea. Photos taken by Rae Gilman Engebretson., 038108
- Ledgers, Series V
  - Accession Sheets., 034129
  - ANT; Archives; Ledger: This is the original (1867) Peabody Museum archaeology and ethnology catalogue, starting at no.1-157 in 1834., 035888
  - Ledger 1; (ANT.000001-3975; ANTPA.03976-4745); 6/11/1908-4/21/1915; PAs 10/27/1910to 3/1/1938; PAs continue from 4745 but not in this volume., 035889
  - Ledger 2. [ant.004001-5000; 12100-12903]. Dates from 1933-1975., 035974
  - Ledger 3. [ant.005101-8,628]. Dates from 1915-1924., 035975
  - Ledger 4. [ant. 008629-013060 (non-contiguous)]. Dates from 1925., 035976
  - Ledger 5. [ant. 013061-15827] Dates from 1930-1931., 035977
  - Ledger 6. [ant. 015830-20473] Dates from 1931-1932., 035978
  - Ledger 7. [ant. 020474-25699] Dates from 1932-1935., 035979
  - Ledger 8. [ant. 025700-31000] Dates from 1935-1937., 035980
  - Ledger 9. [ant. 031001-36851; 11200-11990] Dates from 1934-1936., 035981
  - Ledger 10. [ant. 037001-40953] Date:1936., 035982
  - Ledger 11. [Ant.040954-45087]. 1936. Haiti., 035983
  - Ledger 12. Catalog. [Ant.045088-49000]. 1936. Haiti., 035984
  - Ledger 13. Catalog Ant.049001-52608. 1937-1938., 035985
  - Ledger 14A. Catalog Ant.052609-56031.1938-1942., 035986
  - Ledger 14B. Catalog. Ant.056032-060000. 1942-1945., 035987
  - Ledger 15. Catalog.Ant.060001-061000. 1939-1945., 035988
  - Ledger 16. Catalog. Ant.061001a-069291. 1937-1938. Puerto Rico., 035989
  - Ledger 17. Catalog.Ant.069292-078773. Puerto Rico., 035990
  - Ledger 18. Catalog/ Ant.078774-088261. 1939. Puerto Rico., 035991
  - Ledger 19. Catalog. Ant.088262-097032. 1939. Puerto Rico., 035992
  - Ledger 20. Catalog. Ant.097033-100000. 1944. Puerto Rico., 035993
  - Ledger 21. Catalog. Ant.100001-109567. 1944-1945. Cuba., 035994
  - Ledger 22. Catalog. Ant.109568-110000. 1945. Cuba., 035995
  - Ledger 23. Catalog, Ant.110000-119350. 1941-1943., 035996
  - Ledger 24. Catalog. Ant.119351-128672. 1943-1950., 035997
  - Ledger 25A. Catalog. Ant.128673-130000. 1950-1955., 035998
  - Ledger 25B. Catalog. Ant.130001-139774. 1945-1947., 035999
  - Ledger 26. Catalog. Ant.139775-145256. 1947-1952., 036000
  - Ledger 27. Catalog. Ant.145257-149490. 1952-1956., 036001
  - Ledger 28. Catalog. Ant.150001-158195. 1947-1948., 036002
  - Ledger 29. Catalog. Ant.158196-165501. 1948., 036003
  - Ledger 30. Catalog. Ant.166502-176757. 1948., 036004
  - Ledger 31. Catalog. Ant.176758-186390. 1949-1953., 036005
  - Ledger 32A. Catalog. Ant.186391-192925. 1953-1969., 036006
  - Ledger 32B. Catalog. Ant.192926-197194. 1969-1974., 036007
  - Ledger 33. Catalog. Ant.200001-204877. 1956-1959., 036008
  - Ledger 34. Catalog. Ant. 204878-208265. 1959-1964., 036009
  - Ledger 35. Catalog. Ant.208266-210000. 1964-1971., 036010
  - Ledger 36. Catalog. Ant.210001-219082. 1957-1961., 036011
  - Ledger 37. Catalog. Ant.219083-224850. 1961-1969., 036012
  - Ledger 37A. Catalog. Ant.224851-228444. 1970-1975., 036013
  - Ledger 38. Catalog. Ant.229001-232600. 1961-1972., 036014
  - Ledger 39. Catalog. Ant.232601-236735. 1966-1977., 036015
  - Ledger 39A. Catalog. Ant.236735-240000. 1977-1992., 036016
  - Ledger 40. Catalog. Ant.240001-243470. 1967-1975., 036017
  - Ledger 41A. Catalog. Ant 243471-247706. 1973-1989., 036018
  - Ledger 41B. Catalog. Ant.247707-248000. 1989-1995., 036019
  - Ledger 42. Catalog. Ant.248001-249824. 1976-1984., 036020
  - Ledger 42A. Catalog. Ant.249825-250999. 1985-1995., 036021
  - Ledger 43. Catalog. Ant.251000- 257000. 1976-1999., 036022
  - Ledger 44. Catalog. Ant.257001-258406. 1982-1984., 036023
  - Ledger 45. Catalog. Ant.258407-259999. 1984-1986., 036024
  - Ledger 46. Catalog. Ant.260000-262499. 1984-1998., 036025
  - Ledger 37B. Catalog. Ant.228445-229000. 1975., 036081
  - Ledger 48. Catalog. Ant.264700-266802. 1987-2015., 036281
  - Ledger 50B [ANT.272567-287000] Electronically catalogued 2008. Frank Hole Collection., 036285
  - Ledger 47 [ANT.262500-264699] 1986-2009., 036286
  - Ledger 50A [ANT.270131-272566]. 2007-2008., 036287
  - Ledger 51 [ANT.287001-290854]. 1979-2007., 036288
  - Ledger St. Croix Archaeological Project [ANT.189996-190436]., 036289
  - Ledger 52A [290855-291390] 2007-2008., 036290
- Accession Related Archives, Series VI
  - YPM.01950. 1 box of papers related to Barringer Egypt collection /1950/., 035882
  - YPM.11954. Archives related to accession YPM.11954., 034423
  - YPM.03643 Archives pertaining to accession., 036451
  - YPM.05056. Archives pertaining to the William P. Sargent collection., 036452
  - One Binder of conservation assessment done in August 2012 by O'Connor Art Conservation LLC through the Yale Center for British Art of the Haitian paintings to define scope of work to be done by IPCH conservator Matt Cushman. As of 2/7/17 we still have not received Cushman's final reporst of the work done on the Haitian paintings. All other documentation of the paintings is being done through Cap Sease 2016 onward., 039173
  - 1 archive box of miscellaneous tags and documents out of object boxes, mostly human remains boxes., 039174
  - YPM.07435 Films received form Alec Victor. These are travel films by Professor Shepard Stevens of Yale Art and Architecture Department during the 1920s and 30s., 041141
- Digital Media, Series VII
  - Box of 9 VHS tapes of Richard Hunt carving mask ant.256928 at the Peabody Museum., 036687
  - Sound recordings that have digital files., 039428
- Affiliates, researchers, students,etc., Series VIII
  - Documentation relating to the Division of Anthropology's Connecticut Archaeological Survey from MacCurdy, Rainey and Rouse., 035887
  - Documentation in the Division of Anthropology related to W.K. Simpson excavations in Nubia 1961-1963., 039429
  - Papers and Dissertations related to collections., 041095
- Exhibits, Series IX
  - Spirit Images: The Lidz collection. December 13, 1997-September 30, 1998. Curator: Leopold Pospisil., 037942
- Native American Graves Protection and Repatriation Act, Series X
  Scope and Contents
  Includes 2 boxes of past documentation (pre- 2012).
- Ed Hall Archives, Series XI
  Scanned field notes, slides and correspondence from Edwin S. Hall Jr. Received in the summer of 2015 by Rebekah DeAngelo. Material relates to his field work in Northern Alaska on the Noatak River and Anaktuvuk Pass in the Brooks Range during his undergraduate and graduate Yale work (1958 -1965). Relates to material collected in accession YPM.07136 and possibly others such as YPM.06688. All documentation is electronic, originals retained by Ed Hall, Brockport, NY. The Peabody Museum does not hold copyright to this material, but may use it internally.
  - Ed Hall Archives. Field notebooks from his expeditions to Northern Alaska, first as a Yale undergraduate in 1958, until he completed his Yale Ph. D work in 1968., 036248
  - Ed Hall Archives. Correspondence that arose from his expeditions to Northern Alaska, first as a Yale undergraduate in 1958, until he completed his Yale Ph. D work in 1968., 036378
  - Ed Hall Archives. Grant reports and fundraising letters that arose from E.S. Hall's expeditions to Northern Alaska, first as a Yale undergraduate in 1958, until he completed his Yale Ph. D work in 1968., 036379
  - Ed Hall Archives. Slides created from E.S. Hall's expeditions to Northern Alaska, first as a Yale undergraduate in 1958, until he completed his Yale Ph. D work in 1968., 036380
  - Ed Hall Archives. Maps created from E.S. Hall's expeditions to Northern Alaska, first as a Yale undergraduate in 1958, until he completed his Yale Ph. D work in 1968., 036381
  - Ed Hall Archives. Publications that arose from his expeditions to Northern Alaska, first as a Yale undergraduate in 1958, until he completed his Yale Ph. D work in 1968., 036382
  - Ed Hall Archives. Field notebooks and journals created by mentors and colleagues of E.S. Hall. Notebooks are dated from 1950-1970., 036385
- Campbell Archives, Series XII
  Scanned field notes, slides and correspondence from (Jack) Campbell. Electronic copies of archives collected by Rebekah DeAngelo that pertain to collections held at the Peabody. Some copied from the archives at Gates of the Arctic National Park (GAAR) in the summer of 2014. Some received in the summer of 2015 at the home of Edwin Hall by Ed Hall, Brockport, NY. Material relates to his field work in Northern Alaska at Anaktuvuk Pass in the Brooks Range during his graduate work at Yale (19 -19). The Peabody Museum does not hold copyright to this material, but may use it internally.
  - Campbell Archives. Field notebooks from his expeditions to Northern Alaska, first as an undergraduate in 1947, until he completed his Yale Ph. D work in 1962., 036456
  - Campbell Archives. Correspondence that arose during his field work in Northern Alaska and throughout his professional career from 1947-1990., 036457
  - Campbell Archives. Grant reports and fundraising letters that arose during his field work in Northern Alaska and throughout his professional career from 1947-1990., 036458
  - Campbell Archives. Maps created from J.M. Campbell in Northern Alaska and throughout his professional career from 1947-1970., 036459
  - Campbell Archives. Photographs created from J.M. Campbell in Northern Alaska and throughout his professional career from 1947-1970., 036460
  - Campbell Archives. Publications and research that arose during his field work in Northern Alaska and throughout his professional career from 1947-1970., 036461
- Gary Vescelius, Series XIII
  Vescelius archives: 9 archive boxes of material. Printed inventory includes- Caribbean and South American research.
- [Untitled], Series XIV
  Documents from the Yale University Prehistoric Expediton to Nubia (YUPEN); Peabody Museum accession 7166. One archival box.
  - YUPEN. Crate Lists and Shipment Information, 1964-1965., 042027
  - YUPEN. History of the Yale University Prehistoric Expedition to Nubia, 1962-1965 by Charles A. Reed., 042026
  - YUPEN. Maps., 042028
  - YUPEN. General collection notes., 042029
  - YUPEN. Correspondence., 042030
  - YUPEN. Publications., 042037
  - YUPEN. Student papers., 042038
  - YUPEN. Oversize Maps., 042134
- [Untitled], Series XV
  Documents from the Yale University Prehistoric Expediton to Nubia (YUPEN): Materials received from the University of California, Davis, as part of ANTMISC.000550. Peabody Museum accession 7166. Two archival boxes of documents; two boxes of photos, slides and negatives; one bankers box of binders and books; two map tubes; assorted map folders.
  - YUPEN. Proposals, press releases, and preliminary reports., 042046
  - YUPEN. Expedition staff curriculum vitae., 042047
  - YUPEN. Field Notes., 042048
  - YUPEN. Correspondence., 042049
  - YUPEN. General Collection Notes., 042050
  - YUPEN. Publications., 042051
  - YUPEN. Student Papers., 042052
  - YUPEN. Artifact Inventory - Gebel Sisileh 2B., 042053
  - YUPEN. Shipping Documents., 042068
  - YUPEN. Maps., 042089
  - YUPEN. Negatives. Kurkur Oasis. 4 negatives used in David Boloyan's thesis., 042112
  - YUPEN. Photographs. 22 Field Photos from Gebel Sisileh 2B. Originally found in brown envelope labeled: "July 29, 1964", Baumhoff, Anthropology"., 042113
  - YUPEN. Photographs. 104 Field Photos from Gebel Sisileh 2B., 042114
  - YUPEN. Photographs. 4 Miscellaneous Field Photos Developed from Negatives in GRA 2 and GRA 3., 042115
  - YUPEN. Negatives. 12 negatives from Gebel Sisileh. 13.5cm x 10 cm. In envelope labeled "GRA 1 / Gebel Sesile / 1962-63 expedition". Negatives individually numbered GRA 1/1 to 1/12., 042136
  - YUPEN. Negatives. 12 negatives from Gebel Sisileh. 13.5cm x 10 cm. In envelope labeled "GRA 2 / Gebel Sesile / '62-63 expedition". Negatives individually numbered GRA 2/1 to 2/12., 042137
  - YUPEN. Negatives. 12 negatives from Gebel Sisileh. 13.5cm x 10 cm. In envelope labeled "GRA 3 / Gebel Sesile / '62-63 expedition". Negatives individually numbered GRA 3/1 to 3/12., 042138
  - YUPEN. Negatives. 12 negatives from Gebel Sisileh.13.5cm x 10 cm. In envelope labeled "GRA 4 / Gebel Sesile / '62-63 expedition". Negatives individually numbered GRA 4/1 to 4/12., 042139
  - YUPEN. Negatives. 12 negatives from Gebel Sisileh. 13.5cm x 10 cm. In envelope labeled "GRA 5 / Gebel Sesile / '62-63 expedition". Negatives individually numbered GRA 5/1 to 5/12., 042140
  - YUPEN. Negatives. 25 images of book plates, maps, and artifact images. Found in envelope labeled: "Baumhoff / 3-13-64 / Anthro / 771"., 042141
  - YUPEN. 35mm negative strips and envelope, Gebel Sisileh 2B. Film roll WA 1; 33 exposures on 7 strips. Photos taken December 12, 1962 to January 24, 1963., 042142
  - YUPEN. 35mm negative strips and envelope, Gebel Sisileh 2B. Film roll WA 2; 19 exposures on 6 strips. Photos taken January 28, 1963 to February 12, 1963., 042143
  - YUPEN. 35mm negative strips and envelope, Gebel Sisileh 2B. Film roll WA 3; 34 exposures on 6 strips. Photos taken February 13, 1963 to March 7, 1963., 042144
  - YUPEN. 35mm negative strips and envelope, Gebel Sisileh 2B. Film roll WA 4; 28 exposures on 5 strips. Photos taken March 7, 1963 to March 20, 1963., 042145
  - YUPEN. 35mm negatives, envelope, and contact sheet. AN-38A. 18 exposures on 3 strips., 042146
  - YUPEN. Negatives, Gebel Sisileh 2B. 106 medium format negative exposures on 10 sheets., 042147
  - YUPEN. 35mm slides. Gebel Sisileh 2B. 35 slides on 2 sheets. Artifact and site images., 042148